Guide to the Leopold Haimson papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series III: Menshevik Project,1890s-1977(Inter-University Project on the History of Menshevik Movement)
  - Subseries III.3: Archive on the History of Menshevism, 1898-1972
    - Sub-subseries III.3.1: Menshevik Documents
      - Letters and statements by Mensheviks, 1885-1942
        - Martov, Iulii
          - Articles:
            - "Stranichka vospominanii" (Box 25, Folder 17)
              (typescript of an article published in Vpered, 1918)
        - Plekhanov, Georgii. Correspondence with P.B.Aksel'rod: see Aksel'rod--Correspondence with Plekhanov (Box 24, Folder 12; Box 25, Folder 1)
        - Zasulich, Vera:
          - "Organizatsiia, partiia, dvizhenie". Article published in Iskra, July 1904, (typescript) (Box 25, Folder 18)
          - Speech of her attorney during her trial, (tear-sheets from pamphlet) (Box 25, Folder 18)
      - Meetings, resolutions, and letters to the organizations, 1904-1920
        (organized in chronological order)
        - 1904-1905, (carbon copies of typescript)
          (documents from Boris Nikolaevsky archive)
          - Letters to party organizations by Iskra and others (Box 26, Folder 1)
          - Resolutions (Box 26, Folder 1)
        - 1910-1911Letters to members and resolutions, (photostats and photocopies) (Box 26, Folder 2-2A)
        - 1917-1918Resolutions of RSDRP and articles (Box 26, Folder 3)
          (mostly copied from "Rabochaia gazeta")
        - 1919-1920Sbornik rezoliutsii i tezisov Ts.K. RSDRP i partiinykh soveshchanii (Box 26, Folder 4)
          (photocopy of collection published in Kharkov, 1920)
      - Meetings abroad, past 1917
        - English delegation: documents, 1920 see Series XVI: Ovesize Materials--Subseries XVI.1: Mensheviks documents (Box 166)
        - In the Socialist International
          - Resolutions de la Conference Internationale Ouvriere et Socialiste de Berne, February 1919 (Box 26, Folder 5)
          - Otchet o sobranii Berlinskogo kluba im. Iu.O.Martova, 1932 (Box 26, Folder 6)
          - Protokoll der Internationalen Sozialistischen Konferenz in Wien, February 1921 (Box 26, Folder 7)
          - Protocols of the Convention of the Second International (Box 26, Folder 8)
        - RSDRP delegation abroad: Resolutions from meetings during 1922-1942 (Box 26, Folder 9-13)
      - Bibliography: Guides to source material and literature on Menshevik history, (typescripts and printed material)
        - Bibliography for the History of Menshevism, (indexes, directories, lists, etc.) (Box 27, Folder 1-2)
        - Bibliography on the History of Menshevism prepared by Anna Burgina with assistance of B.Nikolaevsky: see Sub-subseries III.3.4: Biographical Dictionary (Box 53, Folders 4-6)
        - Card catalog: see Series X: Research and Reference Materials--Subseries X.1: Bibliography--Card catalog (Boxes 102-114)
        - Guide to Menshevik periodical publications (Box 27, Folder 3)
        - Material for Menshevik bibliography, (lists, book reviews, etc) (Box 27, Folder 4)
        - List of articles by P.B.Aksel'rod, prepared by A.N.Potresov, 1914 (Box 27, Folder 5)
        - Russkaia politicheskaia literatura za granitsei: sotsial-demokraticheskie izdaniia, (photocopy) (Box 27, Folder 5A)
      - Reference and research material, 1906-1969, (photocopies, typescript, printed materials)
        (in alphabetical order)
        - Articles from "Pravda" of 1921 (Box 27, Folder 6)
        - Grundlagen der russischen Labor Supply Policy, 1943 (Box 27, Folder 7)
        - Izveshchenie o VII s'ezde Bunda, 1906, (photocopy) (Box 27, Folder 8)
        - Mensheviks trial of 1931 see Protsess men'shevikov
        - Obzor partii, primykaiushchikh k Rossiiskoi Sotsial-Demokraticheskoi Rabochei Partii (Box 27, Folder 9)
        - Partiia Sotsialistov-Revoliutsionerov. Protocoly Pervago s'ezda Partii Sotsialistov-Revoliutsionerov, 1905, (photocopy) (Box 27, Folder 10)
          (See also: Chernov, Viktor. "K istorii partii sotsialistov-revoliutsionerov." Russkaia mysl', December 21, 1967-January 11, 1968. Series XVI: Oversize Materials--Subseries XVI: Mensheviks documents, Box 167, Folder 1)
        - Protsess men'shevikov. "Postanovlenie Prezidiuma TSIK Soiuza SSR o lishenii grazhdanstva Soiuza SSR." Pravda,February 22, 1932, (photocopy of newspaper clipping) (Box 27, Folder 10a)
          (See also: Iakubovich, Mikhail. "Pis'mo General'nomu Prokuroru SSSR." Novoe russkoe slovo, October 11, 1969. Series XVI: Ovesize materials--Subseries XVI: Mensheviks documents,Box 167, Folder 2)
        - Rakovskii, Khristian. "Dangers professionnels", 1928, (open letter to Valentinov, photocopy of publication) (Box 27, Folder 11)
        - Sekretnaia zapiska Departamenta politsii o levom dvizhenii v Rossii vo vremia voiny, 1 March 1916 (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Sub-subseries III.3.2: Interviews, 1960-1968
      This sub-subseries contains transcripts of audio interviews with prominent Mensheviks conducted by associates of the Project (typescripts before and after correction, some with holograph corrections, and holograph notes), mostly in Russian, some with English translation. Arranged alphabetically by interviewee last name. Audio records of interviews (reel-to-reel audio tapes) were removed and stored along with other audio materials (see Series XIV: Audio materials).
      - Transcripts:
        - Abramovich, Rafael, undated (Box 27, Folder 13)
          (interviewed by ProA. Wildman; incomplete)
        - Arsenidze, Razhden (asa Misha),July-August 1961, (7 interviews)
          - #1-3 (Box 27, Folder 14-17)
          - #4-7 (Box 28, Folder 1-7)
          - Supplementary interviews #1-5 (Box 28, Folder 8)
        - Dan, Lidiia
          (interviewed by ProA. Wildman and L. Haimson)
          - Interviews taken by A. Wildman,February-May 1960, (9 interviews)
            - #1-3 (Box 28, Folder 9-11)
            - #4-9 (Box 29, Folder 1-6)
          - Interviews taken by L. Haimson, 1960-1962
            (Interviews #1-22 in Russian with English translation)
            - In Russian:
              - #1-5 (Box 29, Folder 7-11)
              - #6-13 (Box 30, Folder 1-8)
              - #14-22 (Box 31, Folder 1-9)
              - #23-24 (Box 32, Folder 1-2)
            - English translation:
              - #1-8 (Box 32, Folder 3-10)
              - #9-22 (Box 33, Folder 1-14)
          - Comments and Queries:
            - Sapir, Boris. Comments on the interviews with L. Dan (Box 33, Folder 15)
            - Queries by copyist/translators (Box 33, Folder 16)
              (including 1 letter)
        - Denike, Iurii. 19 interviews, 1961-1962
          (Interviews #1-15 in Russian with English translations, some include translators' queries)
          - In Russian: # 1-13 (Box 34, Folder 1-13)
          - In Russian: # 14-19 (Box 35, Folder 1-6)
          - English translation and queries: #1-9 (Box 35, Folder 7-14)
          - English translation and queries: #10-15 (Box 36, Folder 1-5)
        - Dvinov, Boris., 1960, (2 interviews) (Box 36, Folder 6)
        - Eradze, Georgii, 1961-1962, (17 interviews) (Box 36, Folder 7-12)
        - Gegechkori, Evgenii, 1966, (holograph notes) (Box 36, Folder 13)
          (Interviewed by Boris Nikolaevsky
        - Gerb, Liudvig, 1960 (Box 36, Folder 14)
          (Interviewed by Solomon Schwarz and Walter Sablinskii)
        - Gol'denberg, IA.M. and E.S., 1960, (5 interviews) (Box 37, Folder 1-4)
          (Interviewed by Walter Sablinskii)
        - Gol'dman, Il'ia. 1961 (Box 37, Folder 5)
        - Gol'dshtein, Anatolii, 1961 (Box 37, Folder 6)
        - Kamermakher, Iuliia Abramovna. 1960 (Box 37, Folder 7)
          (wife of Mark Kamermakher, aka Kefali)
        - Minkov, Isai, 1960-1961, (3 interviews) (Box 37, Folder 8)
        - Nikolaevsky, Boris, 1960-1963, (24 interviews)
          (Interviews #1-8: in Russian with English translations. Interviews #7-18: there are no originals, just photocopies. Some translations contain translators' comments and queries. Also contain some related correspondence)
          - In Russian: #1-6 (Box 37, Folder 9-14)
          - In Russian: #7-24 (Box 38, Folder 1-10)
          - English translation and queries: #1 (Box 38, Folder 11-12)
          - English translation and queries: # 2-8 (Box 39, Folder 1-9)
        - Rozenblat, Petr, 1960 (Box 39, Folder 10)
          (Interviewed by L.Haimson)
        - Rozenblat, Sara, 1960-1961, (3 interviews) (Box 39, Folder 11-13)
        - Schwarz, Solomon. 1962, (2 interviews) (Box 40, Folder 1-2)
        - Stensel', Elena Osipovna, 1960 (Box 40, Folder 3-4)
          (Interviewed by Walter Sablinskii. See also interview #1 with Sigizmund Stensel')
        - Stensel', Sigizmund (Zigmund), 1960 (Box 40, Folder 5-6)
          (Interviewed by Allan Wildman and Walter Sablinskii)
        - Shvarts: see Schwarz
        - Tyrkova-Williams, Ariadna and A. Borman, 1960 (Box 40, Folder 7)
        - Volosov, Boris Isaevich, 1960-1961, (3 interviews) (Box 40, Folder 8-10)
      - Audiorecords, (reel-to-reel tapes) (Box 161-162)
        (stored in Boxes 161-162)
        - Arsenidze, Razhden. Interviews #1-5, (5 reels) (Box 161)
          (2 interviews recorded on the tape with Eradze's interviews)
        - Eradze, Georgii. Interviews #5-8; 11-18, (6 reels) (Box 161)
        - Tsuladze, Vasilii (Box 161)
          (joint interview with Arsenidze)
        - Zhordania, Inna, (3 reels) (Box 161)
        - Russian interviews of 1968, (9 reels) (Box 162)
          (these interviews may not be related to the Menshevik Project)
    - Sub-subseries III.3.3: Writings and Publications,1950s-1972
      This sub-subseries consists mostly of manuscripts and publications of the memoirs and case-studies for the Project. Also included are articles, monographs, interviews, book reviews, comments on works. Drafts, typescripts, publications; some with holograph corrections; some in multiple copies. Writings by Georgian Mensheviks are part of Sub-subseries III.3.7: Georgian collection (boxes 55-57). More writings by Mensheviks are in Sub-subseries III.3.6: Seminars and Sub-subseries III.3.8: Sotsialisticheskii vestnik records. In alphabetical order by author's name.
      - Abramovich, Rafael
        - Men'sheviki i sotsialisticheskii internatsional (1918-1940 g.g.)
          - Photocopy of typescript with holograph notes (Box 41, Folder 1-2)
          - Work outline, drafts, notes (Box 41, Folder 3)
        - Soviet Revolution (book reviews) (Box 41, Folder 4)
        - Haimson's notes on Abramovich's manuscript (Box 41, Folder 5)
      - Aleksandrova, Vera. Perezhitoe (1917-1921 g.g.)
        - Typescript with extensive holograph notes (Box 41, Folder 6)
        - Publication (Box 41, Folder 7)
          (Paper No. 12. New York, September 1962)
      - Anan'in, E.L. Iz vospominanii revoliutsionera, 1905-1923g.g.
        - Typescript of part 2 (Box 41, Folder 8)
        - Publication (Box 41, Folder 9)
          (Paper No. 7. New York, October 1961)
      - Aronson, Grigorii
        - Dvizhenie upolnomochennykh ot rabochikh fabric i zavodov v 1918 godu: K kharakteristike nastroenii rabochego klassa Rossii v pervuiu polovinu 1918 g. New York, 1960 (Box 42, Folder 1)
        - E.D.Kuskova: portret obshchestvennogo deiatelia, 1950s, (typescript) (Box 42, Folder 2)
        - K istorii pravogo techeniia sredi men'shevikov
          - Work outline (Box 42, Folder 3)
          - Publication (Box 42, Folder 4)
            (Paper No. 4. New York, August 1960)
          - Comments by B. Dvinov, (typescript) (Box 42, Folder 5)
        - Men'shevizm v 1905-1914g.g., (typescript with holograph corrections) (Box 42, Folder 6)
        - Revoliutsionnaia iunost': vospominaniia, 1903-1917. Paper No. 6. New York, August 1961 (Box 42, Folder 7-8)
        - V nemetskoi okkupatsii: fevral'-iiun' 1918 g., (photocopy of typescript with holograph corrections) (Box 42, Folder 9)
        - Zamechaniia k rabote Volina: see Volin (Box 50, Folders 11-12)
        - Bibliography of Aronson's works
          - Works published in Novyi zhurnal (Box 42, Folder 10)
            (by L.Haimson)
          - Works in Yiddish (Box 42, Folder 10)
      - Dalin, David
        - Men'shevistskaia partiia posle Oktiabr'skogo perevorota
          - Work outline (Box 43, Folder 1)
          - Haimson's comments, (holograph notes) (Box 43, Folder 1)
        - Men'shevizm v period sovetskoi vlasti
          - Typescript with holograph corrections (Box 43, Folder 2-9)
          - Typescript with holograph corrections (cont.) (Box 44, Folder 1)
        - Comments and corrections on Dalin's works by Iu.Denike, A.Erlikh, L.Haimson, M.Raeff, and B. Sapir, 1961-1963 (Box 44, Folder 2)
      - Dan, Lidiia. Iz vstrech s Veroi Nikolaevnoi Figner
        - Typescript with holograph correction (Box 44, Folder 3)
        - Publication (Box 44, Folder 4)
          (New York, August 1961)
      - Denike, Iurii
        - 1917 v tsentre i na mestakh: parallelism, razlichiia, kontrasty (Box 44, Folder 5)
          (work outline)
        - Kazan' 1907-1909, (typescript) (Box 44, Folder 6)
        - Men'sheviki v 1917 godu (v strane)
          - Work outline (Box 44, Folder 7)
          - Holograph manuscript (Box 44, Folder 8)
          - Typescript (Box 44, Folder 9)
        - Posle razgroma Uchreditel'nogo sobraniia, (typescript) (Box 44, Folder 10)
        - Comments on Dalin's manuscript: see Dalin (Box 44, Folder 2)
      - Dubnova-Erlikh, Sofiia. Obshchestvennyi oblik zhurnala "Letopis'." Paper No. 14. New York, July 1963 (Box 44, Folder 11)
      - Dvinov, Boris (aka Boris Gurevich)
        - From legality to underground (Ot legal'nosti k podpol'iu)
          - Name index and notes, (typescript) (Box 44, Folder 12)
          - Preface by L.Haimson, (typescript with holograph corrections; galley proofs with holograph corrections) (Box 44, Folder 13)
          - "Ot avtora", (photocopy of typescript) (Box 44, Folder 14)
          - "Vvedenie" by B. Sapir, (photocopy of typescript) (Box 44, Folder 14)
        - Monolith: the Communist Party of the Soviet Union and the conflicts within it (Box 45, Folder 1)
          (outline)
        - Moskovskii Sovet rabochikh deputatov 1917-1922. Vospominaniia (Box 45, Folder 2-5)
          - Publication (Box 45, Folder 2-3)
            (Paper No.1. New York, October 1961)
          - Preface and Afterward, (typescript) (Box 45, Folder 4)
          - Comments on critique received during the seminar of 21 January 1960 (Box 45, Folder 5)
        - Ot legal'nosti k podpol'iu: see From legality to underground
        - Pervaia mirovaia voina i rossiiskaia sotsial-demokratiia
          - Publication (Box 45, Folder 6-7)
            (Paper No. 10. New York, August 1962)
          - Work outline (Box 45, Folder 8)
          - Typescript (Box 45, Folder 9-12)
          - Comments on Dvinov's work by L.Haimson and I.Kamermakher (Box 45, Folder 13)
            (including Kamermakher’s letter to Klavdiia Gorokhovets, March 21, 1960)
        - Shtrikhi moei zhizni. Autobiography: see Sub-subseries III.3.4: Biographical Dictionary--Personal files--Dvinov (Box 52, Folder 8), (holograph manuscript and typescript)
        - Zamechaniia k rabote G.IA. Aronsona "K istorii pravogo techeniia sredi men'shevikov": see Aronson. K istorii pravogo techeniia sredi men'shevikov (Box 42, Folder 5)
        - Zamechaniia k rabote Volina: see Volin (Box 50, Folders 11-12)
      - Estrin, Samuil. Vospominaniia, 1962, (typescript with extensive holograph notes) (Box 46, Folder 1)
      - Garvi, Petr (aka Bronshtein). Memoirs
        - Peterburg 1906 goda, (typescript) (Box 46, Folder 2-3)
        - Unpublished memoirs on 1907-1917including "Siluety", (typescript) (Box 46, Folder 4-6)
        - Vospominaniia: Peterburg - 1906 g. Peterburg - Odessa - Vena - 1912 g. New York, December 1961, (publication) (Box 46, Folder 7)
      - Gerts, Jacob Sholem
        - "Neskol'ko dopolnitel'nykh zamechanii o zubatovshchine v Minske", (typescript) (Box 46, Folder 8)
        - "Zubatovshchina v Minske: Neskol'ko zamechanii po povodu utverzhdenii S.M.Shvartsa," in Zubatovshchina v Minske by Ia.Gerts, S. Shvarts (Box 46, Folder 8)
          (New York, July-August 1962)
      - Grinfel'd, Iudif'. Iz vospominanii o bor'be za svobodu i narodovlastie v Odesse 1918-1920 g.g. Paper No. 9. New York, June 1962, (2 copies) (Box 46, Folder 9)
      - Jasny, Naum
        - Preface, (typescript with holograph corrections) (Box 46, Folder 10)
        - "Soviet planner - V.G. Groman," 1954, (reprint) (Box 46, Folder 10)
      - Khinoi, Mark
        - U istokov men'shevizma. Paper No. 3. New York, May 1960, (2 copies) (Box 46, Folder 11)
        - V podpol'nykh tipografiiakh tsarskoi Rossii. Paper No. 2. New York, May 1960 (Box 46, Folder 12)
      - Kuchin-Oranskii, Georgii. Zapiski, (photocopy of typescript) (Box 47, Folder 1)
      - Lande, Lev
        - Chapter 5 consolidation of Bolshevik rule,", (photocopy of typescript) (Box 47, Folder 2)
        - "Men'shevistskaia partiia posle Oktiabr'skogo perevorota": see Dalin, D.--Men'shevistskaia partiia posle Oktiabr'skogo perevorota,Box 43, Folder 1
        - Men'shevizm v 1917 godu, (typescript and holograph manuscript)
          - Manuscript (Box 47, Folder 3)
          - Additions and comments (Box 47, Folder 4-5)
        - "RSDRP posle Oktiabr'skogo perevorota" (Box 47, Folder 6)
          (summary of 2 chapters)
      - Nikolaevsky, Boris
        - "Gruppa sibirskikh tsimmerval'distov", (photocopy of typescript) (Box 47, Folder 7)
        - "Men'sheviki posle Oktiabr'skogo perevorota", (photocopy of typescript) (Box 47, Folder 8)
        - "Men'sheviki v period voennogo kommunizma: 1918-21 gg.", (typescript) (Box 47, Folder 9-10)
        - "RSDRP (men'sheviki) v pervye gody revoliutsii: 1917-1918gg.", (photocopy of typescript) (Box 47, Folder 11)
        - "RSDRP (men'sheviki) za vremia s dekabria 1917 po iiul' 1918 g.: predvaritel'naia spravka", (typescript) (Box 47, Folder 12)
        - "Stranitsy istorii: Bukharin ob oppozitsii Stalinu." Interview with B.Nikolaevsky, (reprint) (Box 47, Folder 13)
        - Book review on Nikolaevsky's "The letter of an Old Bolshevik", (photocopy) (Box 47, Folder 13)
        - Bibliography of his works (Box 47, Folder 14)
        - Haimson's notes on Nikolaevsky (Box 47, Folder 15)
      - Sapir, Boris
        - Notes and reflections on the history of Menshevizm, (xerox of typescript) (Box 47, Folder 16)
        - "Petr Lavrov," 1972, (reprint) (Box 47, Folder 17)
          (with inscription)
        - "Posledniaia glava", (typescript with holograph corrections) (Box 47, Folder 18)
        - Predshestvenniki men'shevizma (aka "Predtechi i zarozhdenie men'shevizma")
          - Preliminary outline (Box 48, Folder 1)
          - Glava 1, (multiple copies with holograph corrections) (Box 48, Folder 2-3)
        - Comments on Dalin's manuscript: see Dalin (Box 44, Folder 2)
        - Introduction to Dvinov's Ot legal'nosti k podpol'iu: see Dvinov--From Legality to Underground (Box 44, Folder 14)
        - Zamechaniia k rabote Volina: see Volin (Box 50, Folders 11-12)
      - Schwarz, Solomon
        - "Agriculture: the Curtain is Lifted." Reprint from Problems of Communism,March-April 1966 (Box 48, Folder 4)
        - "Aldanov", (typescript of article) (Box 48, Folder 5)
        - "Fabrichno-zavodskie komitety i profsoiuzy v Rossii v pervye gody revoliutsii", (typescript) (Box 48, Folder 6)
        - "Ideia sotsial'noi avtonomii v sisteme strakhovaniia rabochikh i strakhovoe rabochee dvizhenie v Rossii v 1912-1914godakh", (typescript) (Box 48, Folder 7)
        - "Materialy o razvitii program ekonomicheskoi politiki v 1917-1918godakh", (typescript) (Box 48, Folder 8)
        - "Men'shevizm i bol'shevism v ikh otnoshenii k massovomu rabochemu dvizheniiu"
          - Work outline and memo (Box 48, Folder 9)
          - Manuscript, (typescript with holograph notes; holograph manuscript)
            - Glava 1: Na poroge 1905 goda (Box 48, Folder 10)
            - 1905 god (Box 48, Folder 11-16)
              (Chapters: Osnovnaia kontseptsiia revoliutsii; Komissiia Shidlovskogo; Sovety rabochikh deputatov; Organizatsionnye problemy sotsial-demokratii)
        - "Otvet IA.SH. Gertsu"
          - Holograph manuscript and typescript with holograph corrections (Box 49, Folder 1)
          - Zubatovshchina v Minske by Ia.Gerts, S. Shvarts, New York,July-August 1962, (publication) (Box 49, Folder 2)
        - Russian Revolution of 1905 the Workers’ Movement and the Formation of Bolshevism and Menshevism (Box 49, Folder 3)
          (Russkaia revoliutsiia 1905 goda)
          - Preface by L. Haimson, (typescript with holograph notes) (Box 49, Folder 3)
            (In English)
        - "Russia's Economy", (Article; newspaper clipping) (Box 49, Folder 4)
      - Shishkin, Matvei. Iz vospominanii kooperativnykh i politicheskikh. Paper No. 5. New York, November 1960 (Box 49, Folder 5)
      - Shvarts: see Schwarz
      - Stat'i, posviashchennye IU.O. Martovu sobrannye iz raznykh istochnikov I.M. Getslerom dlia Inter-University Project on the history of the menshvik movement. New York, November 1961 (Box 49, Folder 6)
      - Valentinov, Nikolai (aka Vol'skii)
        - "Men'shevizm i ego propaganda idei revoliutsionnogo samoupravleniia", (photocopy of typescript) (Box 49, Folder 7)
        - "Men'shevizm i problema vlasti", (typescript with holograph notes) (Box 49, Folder 8)
        - "O liudiakh podpol'ia", (typescript with holograph corrections) (Box 49, Folder 9)
        - "Obshcherusskaia konferentsiia men'shevikov i Plekhanov", (typescript with holograph notes) (Box 49, Folder 10)
        - Rozhdenie men'shevizma, (typescript with holograph notes) (Box 49, Folder 11-13)
      - Voitinskaia, Emma: see Woytinsky, Emma
      - Volin, Semen
        - Deiatel'nost' men'shevikov v profsoiuzakh pri sovetskoi vlasti
          - Work outline (Box 49, Folder 14)
          - Publication (Box 49, Folder 15-16)
            (Paper No. 13. New York, October 1962)
        - Men'sheviki na Ukraine (1917-1921). Paper No. 11. New York, September 1962, (publication) (Box 49, Folder 17)
        - "Men'shevistskaia partiia posle Oktiabr'skogo perevorota": see Dalin, D.-- Men'shevistskaia partiia posle Oktiabr'skogo perevorota (Box 43, Folder 1)
        - Men'shevizm v 20-kh i nachale 30-kh godov, (typescript draft with holograph notes, notes, final typescript)
          - Preliminary plan, drafts (Box 50, Folder 1)
          - Draft, (holograph notes, typescript with holograph corrections) (Box 50, Folder 2-7)
            (Also includes a letter of 22 April 1964 to Leopold Haimson from Iuliia Kamermakher)
          - Final typescript (Box 50, Folder 8-10)
        - Comments on Volin's works by G. Aronson, B. Dvinov, L. Haimson, B. Sapir (Box 50, Folder 11-12)
      - Vol'skii, N.: see Valentinov
      - Woytinsky, Emma. Vstuplenie k "Istorii Peterburgskogo Soveta bezrabotnykh" Vladimira Voitinskogo (Box 50, Folder 13)
    - Sub-subseries III.3.4: "Biographical Dictionary,"1940s-1962